<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cybertraining – pycharm</title>
    <link>/tags/pycharm/</link>
    <description>Recent content in pycharm on Cybertraining</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	  <atom:link href="/tags/pycharm/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
      
        
      
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Docs: Installing PyCharm Professional for Free</title>
      <link>/docs/tutorial/reu/pycharm/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/docs/tutorial/reu/pycharm/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        

&lt;div class=&#34;pageinfo pageinfo-primary&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tutorial teaches how to get PyCharm Professional for free on
Windows 10 using a university email address. You can follow a similar
process on Linux and macOS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contents&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;toc&#34;&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#steps&#34;&gt;Steps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keywords:&lt;/strong&gt; pycharm&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;steps&#34;&gt;Steps&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click the following image to be redirected to a YouTube video tutorial for installing PyCharm Professional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/QPESX-VBnEU&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please ensure that you qualify. This includes you having a valid
educational email or be part of an open-source project. Make sure to
explore the license agreements for PyCharm as they may change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open up a web browser and search &lt;code&gt;pycharm&lt;/code&gt;. Look under the link from &lt;code&gt;jetbrains.com&lt;/code&gt; and click &lt;code&gt;Download PyCharm&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click the &lt;strong&gt;blue&lt;/strong&gt; button that reads &lt;code&gt;Download&lt;/code&gt; under Professional. Wait for the download to complete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open the completely downloaded file and click &lt;code&gt;Yes&lt;/code&gt; on the UAC prompt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you have a school computer, please refer to the note under step 5 of the Windows section in the Python tutorial found here:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cybertraining-dsc/cybertraining-dsc.github.io/blob/main/content/en/docs/tutorial/reu/python/index.md&#34;&gt;https://github.com/cybertraining-dsc/cybertraining-dsc.github.io/blob/main/content/en/docs/tutorial/reu/python/index.md&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click &lt;code&gt;Next&lt;/code&gt;, click &lt;code&gt;Next&lt;/code&gt; again, and check the box that reads &lt;code&gt;Add launchers dir to the PATH&lt;/code&gt;. You can also
create a Desktop Shortcut and create the &lt;code&gt;.py&lt;/code&gt; association if you would like. The association changes which program,
by default, opens &lt;code&gt;.py&lt;/code&gt; files on your computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click &lt;code&gt;Next&lt;/code&gt; and then click &lt;code&gt;Install&lt;/code&gt;. Wait for the green progress bar to complete. Then, you must restart your
computer after making sure all of your programs are saved and closed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open PyCharm either by clicking on the Desktop shortcut you might have made or hit the Windows key and type
&lt;code&gt;PyCharm&lt;/code&gt; and choose the program from the search results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check the box that says &lt;code&gt;I confirm that I have read and accept the terms...&lt;/code&gt; after agreeing to the terms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click &lt;code&gt;Continue&lt;/code&gt;. You can choose to send anonymous statistics, if you want to; click the option you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click the hyperlink that says &lt;code&gt;Buy license&lt;/code&gt; in the top right of the window. Do not worry — you will not be spending
a cent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click the person icon in the top right of the page (if you cannot find this person icon, then click this link
and hopefully, it still works: &lt;a href=&#34;https://account.jetbrains.com/login&#34;&gt;https://account.jetbrains.com/login&lt;/a&gt; ).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create a JetBrains account by entering your university email address. Click &lt;code&gt;Sign Up&lt;/code&gt; after entering your email;
then, you have to go on your email and confirm your account in the automated email sent to you. Click &lt;code&gt;Confirm your account&lt;/code&gt; in the email.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Complete the registration form and click &lt;code&gt;Submit&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click &lt;code&gt;Apply for a free student or teacher license&lt;/code&gt;. Scroll down and click the blue button that reads &lt;code&gt;Apply now&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fill out the form using your (educational) email address and real name. Check the boxes if they apply to you. Then
click &lt;code&gt;APPLY FOR FREE PRODUCTS&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;JetBrains should send you an automated email, ideally informing you that your information has been confirmed and
you have been granted a free license. If it does not arrive immediately, wait a few minutes. Go back to PyCharm and sign in with your JetBrains account after receiving this email. Click &lt;code&gt;Activate&lt;/code&gt;. Now you can use PyCharm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Docs: Tutorial on Using venv in PyCharm</title>
      <link>/docs/tutorial/pycharm/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/docs/tutorial/pycharm/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        &lt;p&gt;Jacques Fleischer&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;pageinfo pageinfo-primary&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract&#34;&gt;Abstract&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tutorial teaches how to set PyCharm to use a venv.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contents&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;toc&#34;&gt;
  &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#windows&#34;&gt;Windows&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keywords:&lt;/strong&gt; venv&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;windows&#34;&gt;Windows&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please ensure that you have Git (Git Bash), Python, and PyCharm. If you do not have those, look for the tutorials to install them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tutorial was created with the REU program in mind, where the students are provided with a GitHub repository. If you are not in REU, then you can create a new repository on GitHub and clone that instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click the following image to be redirected to a YouTube video tutorial for setting venv in PyCharm. Please keep in mind that this video follows directions that are somewhat different from the written instructions below. REU students should follow the written instructions over the video. Otherwise, in the video, you should skip to timestamp 8:19 unless you do not have Git or a venv, in which case you should watch the entire video.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/HCotEx_xCfA&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have not already cloned your reu repository, you need to follow a separate tutorial which involves setting up your SSH key on GitHub, which can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cybertraining-dsc/cybertraining-dsc.github.io/blob/main/content/en/docs/tutorial/git/git-ssh/index.md&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open PyCharm. If this is your first time opening PyCharm, then it will say &lt;code&gt;Welcome to PyCharm&lt;/code&gt;. You should have cloned your repo to a particular location on your computer; click &lt;code&gt;Open&lt;/code&gt; and then locate your reu folder. Once you have found it, click on it so it is highlighted in blue and then click &lt;code&gt;OK&lt;/code&gt;. Alternatively, if you have used PyCharm before, your previous project should open, in which case you should click &lt;code&gt;File&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Open...&lt;/code&gt; to open your repo (if it is not already open).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please ensure that you have already configured a venv through Git Bash. If you have not, then read and follow &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cybertraining-dsc/su21-reu-361/blob/main/tutorials/python/venv.md&#34;&gt;this tutorial&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the top-right of PyCharm, click on the button that reads &lt;code&gt;Add Configuration...&lt;/code&gt;. Click &lt;code&gt;Add new...&lt;/code&gt; on the left underneath &lt;code&gt;No run configurations added.&lt;/code&gt; and then scroll and click &lt;code&gt;Python&lt;/code&gt;. Give this a name; you can just type &lt;code&gt;Python venv&lt;/code&gt;. Next to &lt;code&gt;Python interpreter&lt;/code&gt;, choose &lt;code&gt;Python x.x (ENV3)&lt;/code&gt;. The &lt;code&gt;x.x&lt;/code&gt; will depend on which version of Python you have. Then click &lt;code&gt;OK&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The button might not read &lt;code&gt;Add Configuration...&lt;/code&gt;. If you have configured a run configuration previously, then you can create a new one. Click the button right next to the green play button in the top-right of PyCharm. Then, it should say &lt;code&gt;Edit Configurations...&lt;/code&gt; which you must click on. Change the Python interpreter to be the &lt;code&gt;ENV3&lt;/code&gt; one, as outlined in Step #4.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You also have to click &lt;code&gt;Python x.x&lt;/code&gt; in the bottom-right of PyCharm, next to &lt;code&gt;main&lt;/code&gt;. From there, choose &lt;code&gt;Python x.x (ENV3)&lt;/code&gt;. To verify that your virtual environment is working, click on &lt;code&gt;Terminal&lt;/code&gt; in the bottom-left of PyCharm. Click the &lt;code&gt;+&lt;/code&gt; (plus) icon next to Local to start a new terminal. It should say &lt;code&gt;(ENV3)&lt;/code&gt; next to your current working directory. Congratulations!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
