<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Cybertraining – git bash</title><link>/tags/git-bash/</link><description>Recent content in git bash on Cybertraining</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/git-bash/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Docs: Installing Git Bash on Windows 10</title><link>/docs/tutorial/reu/github/git/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/docs/tutorial/reu/github/git/</guid><description>
&lt;div class="pageinfo pageinfo-primary">
&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This tutorial teaches how to install Git and Git Bash.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Contents&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="toc">
&lt;nav id="TableOfContents">
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#windows">Windows&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/nav>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Keywords:&lt;/strong> git&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="windows">Windows&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Click the following image to be redirected to a YouTube video tutorial for installing Git and Git Bash. This same video also includes instructions to create a virtual Python environment, which you can do as well.&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/HCotEx_xCfA" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>To verify whether you have Git, you can press &lt;code>Win + R&lt;/code> on your desktop, type &lt;code>cmd&lt;/code>, and press &lt;code>Enter&lt;/code>. Then type &lt;code>git clone&lt;/code> and press &lt;code>Enter&lt;/code>. If you do not have Git installed, it will say &lt;code>'git' is not recognized as an internal or external command...&lt;/code>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As long as Git does not change up their website and hyperlinks, you should be able to download Git from here and skip to step 2: &lt;a href="https://git-scm.com/downloads">https://git-scm.com/downloads&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Open a web browser and search &lt;code>git&lt;/code>. Look for the result that is from &lt;code>git-scm.com&lt;/code> and click Downloads.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Click &lt;code>Download for Windows&lt;/code>. The download will commence. Please open the file once it is finished downloading.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>The UAC Prompt will appear. Click &lt;code>Yes&lt;/code> because Git is a safe program. It will show you Git&amp;rsquo;s license: a GNU General Public License. Click &lt;code>Next&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>The GNU General Public License means that the program is open-source (free of charge).&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Click &lt;code>Next&lt;/code> to confirm that &lt;code>C:\Program Files\Git&lt;/code> is the directory where you want Git to be installed.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Click &lt;code>Next&lt;/code> unless you would like an icon for Git on the desktop (in which case you can check the box and then click &lt;code>Next&lt;/code>).&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>You will be askes several questions for the setup. We recommend the following settings:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Click &lt;code>Next&lt;/code> to accept the text editor,&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Click &lt;code>Next&lt;/code> again to Let Git decide the default branch name&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Click &lt;code>Next&lt;/code> again to run Git from the command line and 3rd party software,&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Click &lt;code>Next&lt;/code> again to use the OpenSSL library&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Click &lt;code>Next&lt;/code> again to checkout Windows-style,&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Click &lt;code>Next&lt;/code> again to use MinTTY,&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Click &lt;code>Next&lt;/code> again to use the default git pull,&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Click &lt;code>Next&lt;/code> again to use the Git Credential Manager Core,&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Click &lt;code>Next&lt;/code> again to enable file system caching, and then&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Click &lt;code>Install&lt;/code> because we do not need experimental features.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>The progress bar should not take too long to finish. To test if it is installed, you can search for &lt;code>Git Bash&lt;/code> in the Windows search now to run it.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol></description></item></channel></rss>