<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Cybertraining – orthodontics</title><link>/tags/orthodontics/</link><description>Recent content in orthodontics on Cybertraining</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/orthodontics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Report: Project: AI in Orthodontics</title><link>/report/su21-reu-363/project/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/report/su21-reu-363/project/</guid><description>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://github.com/cybertraining-dsc/su21-reu-363/actions">&lt;img src="https://github.com/cybertraining-dsc/su21-reu-363/workflows/Check%20Report/badge.svg" alt="Check Report">&lt;/a>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/cybertraining-dsc/su21-reu-363/actions">&lt;img src="https://github.com/cybertraining-dsc/su21-reu-363/workflows/Status/badge.svg" alt="Status">&lt;/a>
Status: draft, Type: Project&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Whitney McNair, &lt;a href="https://github.com/cybertraining-dsc/su21-reu-363">su21-reu-363&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://github.com/cybertraining-dsc/su21-reu-363/blob/main/project/index.md">Edit&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="pageinfo pageinfo-primary">
&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In this effort we are analzying X-ray images in AI and identify cavitites&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Contents&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="toc">
&lt;nav id="TableOfContents">
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#1-introduction">1. Introduction&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#2-data-sets">2. Data Sets&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#3-using-images">3. Using Images&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#5-example-of-a-ai-algorighm-in-orthodontics">5. Example of a AI algorighm in Orthodontics&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#6-benchmark">6. Benchmark&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#6-conclusion">6. Conclusion&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#8-acknowledgments">8. Acknowledgments&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#9-references">9. References&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/nav>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Keywords:&lt;/strong> ai, orthodontics, x-rays.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="1-introduction">1. Introduction&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Dental field technology capability has increased over the past 25 years, and has helped reduce time, cost, medical errors, and dependence on human expertise[1]. Intelligence in orthodontics can learn, build, remember, understand and recognize designs from techniques used in correcting the teeth like retainers. Dental field can create alternatives, adapt to change and explore experiences with sub-groups of patients[reference]. AI has taken part of the dental field by accurately and efficiently processes the best data from treatments. For smart use of Health Data, machine learning and artificial intelligence (AI) are expected to promote further development of the digital revolution in (dental) medicine using algorithms to simulate human cognition in the analysis of complex data. The performance is better, the higher the degree of repetitive pattern and the larger the amount of accessible data[5].&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="2-data-sets">2. Data Sets&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We found a dataset in kaggle website that is about dental images. The data was collected by Mr. Parth Chokhra. The name of the dataset is Dental Images of kjbjl. The dataset did not have metadata and an explanation of how they collected the data. The data set supports how x-rays of teeth in dentistry becomes artificial intelligence. The Dental Images of kjbjl dataset was used in AI already using autoencoders. Autoencoders are an freely artificial neural network (located in the nervous system) that learns how to accurately encode data and reconstruct the data back from the reduced encoded representation to a representation that is as close to the original input as possible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Describe the data that was in the paper.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;input disabled="" type="checkbox"> What are the challenges with Orthodontics data set? Privacy, HIPAA, Size, Avalibility
Some challenges with Orthodontics data sets with privacy&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>explain how its hard to find&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;input disabled="" type="checkbox"> Datasets can be huge and GitHub has limited space. Only very small datasets should be stored in GitHub.
However, if the data is publicly available you program must contain a download function instead that you customize.
Write it using pythons &lt;code>request&lt;/code>. You will get point deductions if you check-in data sets that are large and do not use
the download function.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="3-using-images">3. Using Images&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;input disabled="" type="checkbox"> Place a cool image into projects images in my directory&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;input disabled="" type="checkbox"> Correct the following link, replace the fa number with my su number and thne chart of png.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;input disabled="" type="checkbox"> If the image has been copied, you must use a reference such as shown in the Figure 1 caption.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://github.com/cybertraining-dsc/fa20-523-314/raw/main/project/images/chart.png" alt="Figure 1">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Figure 1:&lt;/strong> Images can be included in the report, but if they are copied you must cite them &lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Place image of x ray and url of the kaggle images. Talk about what and how etc. the images are about and look like and what you can do with them.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="5-example-of-a-ai-algorighm-in-orthodontics">5. Example of a AI algorighm in Orthodontics&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;input disabled="" type="checkbox"> Identify the concrete data sets that will be used.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;input disabled="" type="checkbox"> Identify the concrete algorighm to analyze the data sets.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Read over google scholar review page on orthondontics about their research and algorighm (if used).&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="6-benchmark">6. Benchmark&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Your project must include a benchmark. The easiest is to use cloudmesh-common &lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Talk about the matrics in the google scholar review says. The matrics that the researchers are using to study the performance of their algorighns or code.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="6-conclusion">6. Conclusion&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>A convincing but not fake conclusion should summarize what the conclusion of the project is.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What the researchers have done in conclusion. &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip; used these algorigns to&amp;hellip;.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="8-acknowledgments">8. Acknowledgments&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;input disabled="" type="checkbox"> Gregor guided me throughout this process.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;input disabled="" type="checkbox"> Carlos guided me throughout this process.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Please add acknowledgments to all that contributed or helped on this project.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="9-references">9. References&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;input disabled="" type="checkbox"> Your report must include at least 6 references. Please use customary academic citation and not just URLs. As we will at
one point automatically change the references from superscript to square brackets it is best to introduce a space before
the first square bracket.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Change 6 reference and replace with google scholar research paper.&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Use of energy explained - Energy use in homes, [Online resource]
&lt;a href="https://www.eia.gov/energyexplained/use-of-energy/electricity-use-in-homes.php">https://www.eia.gov/energyexplained/use-of-energy/electricity-use-in-homes.php&lt;/a>&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>&amp;lt;Bichu, Y.M., Hansa, I., Bichu, A.Y. et al. Applications of artificial intelligence and machine learning in orthodontics: a scoping review. Prog Orthod. 22, 18 (2021).&amp;gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></description></item></channel></rss>