<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cybertraining – plotviz</title>
    <link>/tags/plotviz/</link>
    <description>Recent content in plotviz on Cybertraining</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    
	  <atom:link href="/tags/plotviz/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
      
        
      
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Docs: Plotviz</title>
      <link>/docs/modules/bigdataapplications/2019/applications/plotviz/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/docs/modules/bigdataapplications/2019/applications/plotviz/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE: This an legacy application this has now been replaced by WebPlotViz
which is a web browser based visualization tool which provides added
functionality&amp;rsquo;s.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We introduce Plotviz, a data visualization tool developed at Indiana
University to display 2 and 3 dimensional data. The motivation is that
the human eye is very good at pattern recognition and can &lt;em&gt;see&lt;/em&gt;
structure in data. Although most Big data is higher dimensional than 3,
all can be transformed by dimension reduction techniques to 3D. He gives
several examples to show how the software can be used and what kind of
data can be visualized. This includes individual plots and the
manipulation of multiple synchronized plots.Finally, he describes the
download and software dependency of Plotviz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;using-plotviz-software-for-displaying-point-distributions-in-3d&#34;&gt;Using Plotviz Software for Displaying Point Distributions in 3D&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We introduce Plotviz, a data visualization tool developed at Indiana
University to display 2 and 3 dimensional data. The motivation is that
the human eye is very good at pattern recognition and can &lt;em&gt;see&lt;/em&gt;
structure in data. Although most Big data is higher dimensional than 3,
all can be transformed by dimension reduction techniques to 3D. He gives
several examples to show how the software can be used and what kind of
data can be visualized. This includes individual plots and the
manipulation of multiple synchronized plots. Finally, he describes the
download and software dependency of Plotviz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://iu.app.box.com/s/jypomnrz755xgps5e6iw&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/presentation.png&#34; alt=&#34;Presentation&#34;&gt; Plotviz (34)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Files:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cloudmesh-community/book/blob/master/examples/python/plotviz/fungi-lsu-3-15-to-3-26-zeroidx.pviz&#34;&gt;https://github.com/cloudmesh-community/book/blob/master/examples/python/plotviz/fungi-lsu-3-15-to-3-26-zeroidx.pviz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cloudmesh-community/book/blob/master/examples/python/plotviz/datingrating-originallabels.pviz&#34;&gt;https://github.com/cloudmesh-community/book/blob/master/examples/python/plotviz/datingrating-originallabels.pviz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cloudmesh-community/book/blob/master/examples/python/plotviz/clusterFinal-M30-C28.pviz&#34;&gt;https://github.com/cloudmesh-community/book/blob/master/examples/python/plotviz/clusterFinal-M30-C28.pviz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/cloudmesh-community/book/blob/master/examples/python/plotviz/clusterfinal-m3-c3dating-reclustered.pviz&#34;&gt;https://github.com/cloudmesh-community/book/blob/master/examples/python/plotviz/clusterfinal-m3-c3dating-reclustered.pviz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;motivation-and-introduction-to-use&#34;&gt;Motivation and Introduction to use&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The motivation of Plotviz is that the human eye is very good at pattern
recognition and can &lt;em&gt;see&lt;/em&gt; structure in data. Although most Big data is
higher dimensional than 3, all data can be transformed by dimension
reduction techniques to 3D and one can check analysis like clustering
and/or see structure missed in a computer analysis. The motivations
shows some Cheminformatics examples. The use of Plotviz is started in
slide 4 with a discussion of input file which is either a simple text or
more features (like colors) can be specified in a rich XML syntax.
Plotviz deals with points and their classification (clustering). Next
the protein sequence browser in 3D shows the basic structure of Plotviz
interface. The next two slides explain the core 3D and 2D manipulations
respectively. Note all files used in examples are available to students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://youtu.be/4aQlCmQ1jfY&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/presentation.png&#34; alt=&#34;Presentation&#34;&gt; Motivation (7:58)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;example-of-use-i-cube-and-structured-dataset&#34;&gt;Example of Use I: Cube and Structured Dataset&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially we start with a simple plot of 8 points &amp;ndash; the corners of a
cube in 3 dimensions &amp;ndash; showing basic operations such as
size/color/labels and Legend of points. The second example shows a
dataset (coming from GTM dimension reduction) with significant
structure. This has .pviz and a .txt versions that are compared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://youtu.be/nCTT5mI_j_Q&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/presentation.png&#34; alt=&#34;Presentation&#34;&gt; Example I (9:45)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;example-of-use-ii-proteomics-and-synchronized-rotation&#34;&gt;Example of Use II: Proteomics and Synchronized Rotation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This starts with an examination of a sample of Protein Universe Browser
showing how one uses Plotviz to look at different features of this set
of Protein sequences projected to 3D. Then we show how to compare two
datasets with synchronized rotation of a dataset clustered in 2
different ways; this dataset comes from k Nearest Neighbor discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://youtu.be/lDbIhnLrNkk&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/presentation.png&#34; alt=&#34;Presentation&#34;&gt; Proteomics and Synchronized Rotation (9:14)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;example-of-use-iii-more-features-and-larger-proteomics-sample&#34;&gt;Example of Use III: More Features and larger Proteomics Sample&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This starts by describing use of Labels and Glyphs and the Default mode
in Plotviz. Then we illustrate sophisticated use of these ideas to view
a large Proteomics dataset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://youtu.be/KBkUW_QNSvs&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/presentation.png&#34; alt=&#34;Presentation&#34;&gt; Larger Proteomics Sample (8:37)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;example-of-use-iv-tools-and-examples&#34;&gt;Example of Use IV: Tools and Examples&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This lesson starts by describing the Plotviz tools and then sets up two
examples &amp;ndash; Oil Flow and Trading &amp;ndash; described in PowerPoint. It finishes
with the Plotviz viewing of Oil Flow data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://youtu.be/zp_709imR40&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/presentation.png&#34; alt=&#34;Presentation&#34;&gt; Plotviz I (10:17)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;example-of-use-v-final-examples&#34;&gt;Example of Use V: Final Examples&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This starts with Plotviz looking at Trading example introduced in
previous lesson and then examines solvent data. It finishes with two
large biology examples with 446K and 100K points and each with over 100
clusters. We finish remarks on Plotviz software structure and how to
download. We also remind you that a picture is worth a 1000 words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://youtu.be/FKoCfTJ_cDM&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;images/video.png&#34; alt=&#34;Video&#34;&gt; Plotviz II (14:58)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;resources&#34;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://salsahpc.indiana.edu/pviz3/&#34;&gt;Download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Docs: WebPlotViz</title>
      <link>/docs/modules/bigdataapplications/2019/applications/webplotviz/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/docs/modules/bigdataapplications/2019/applications/webplotviz/</guid>
      <description>
        
        
        &lt;p&gt;WebPlotViz is a browser based visualization tool developed at Indiana University.
This tool allows user to visualize 2D and 3D data points in the web browser.
WebPlotViz was developed as a succesor to the previous visualization tool PlotViz
which was a application which needed to be installed on your machine to be used.
You can find more information about PlotViz at the &lt;a href=&#34;plotviz.md&#34;&gt;PlotViz Section&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;motivation&#34;&gt;Motivation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The motivation of WebPlotViz is similar to PlotViz which is that the human eye
is very good at pattern recognition and can see structure in data. Although
most Big data is higher dimensional than 3, all data can be transformed by
dimension reduction techniques to 3D and one can check analysis like clustering
and/or see structure missed in a computer analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-use&#34;&gt;How to use&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to use WebPlotViz you need to host the application as a server, this
can be done on you local machine or a application server. The source code for
WebPlotViz can be found at the git hub repo &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/DSC-SPIDAL/WebPViz&#34;&gt;WebPlotViz git Repo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However there is a online version that is hosted on Indiana university servers
that you can access and use. The online version is available at &lt;a href=&#34;https://spidal-gw.dsc.soic.indiana.edu/&#34;&gt;WebPlotViz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to use the services of WebPlotViz you would need to first create a
simple account by providing your email and a password. Once the account is
created you can login and upload files to WebPlotViz to be visualized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;uploading-files-to-webplotviz&#34;&gt;Uploading files to WebPlotViz&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While WebPlotViz does accept several file formats as inputs, we will look at the
most simple and easy to use format that users can use. Files are uploaded as
&amp;ldquo;.txt&amp;rdquo; files with the following structure. Each value is separated by a space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Index x_val y_val z_val cluster_id label&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;0  0.155117377  0.011486086  -0.078151964  1  l1&lt;br&gt;
1  0.148366394  0.010782429  -0.076370584  2  l2&lt;br&gt;
2  0.170597667  -0.025115137  -0.082946074  2  l2&lt;br&gt;
3  0.136063907  -0.006670781  -0.082583441  3  l3&lt;br&gt;
4  0.158259943  0.015187686  -0.073592601  5  l5&lt;br&gt;
5  0.162483279  0.014387166  -0.085987414  5  l5&lt;br&gt;
6  0.138651632  0.013358333  -0.062633719  5  l5&lt;br&gt;
7  0.168020213  0.010742307  -0.090281011  5  l5&lt;br&gt;
8  0.15810229  0.007551404  -0.083311109  4  l4&lt;br&gt;
9  0.146878082  0.003858649  -0.071298345  4  l4&lt;br&gt;
10  0.151487542  0.011896318  -0.074281645  4  l4&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have the data file properly formatted you can upload the file through
the WebPlotViz GUI. Once you login to your account you should see a Green
&amp;ldquo;Upload&amp;rdquo; button on the top left corner. Once you press it you would see a
form that would allow you to choose the file, provide a description and select a
group to which the file needs to be categorized into. If you do not want to
assign a group you can simply use the default group which is picked by default&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have uploaded the file the file should appear in the list of plots
under the heading &amp;ldquo;Artifacts&amp;rdquo;. Then you can click on the name or the &amp;ldquo;View&amp;rdquo;
link to view the plot. Clicking on &amp;ldquo;View&amp;rdquo; will directly take you to the full
view of the plot while clicking on the name will show and summary of the plot
with a smaller view of the plot (Plot controls are not available in the smaller
view). You can view how the sample dataset looks like after uploading at the
following link. @fig:webpviz-11 shows a screen shot of the plot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://spidal-gw.dsc.soic.indiana.edu/public/resultsets/2083856374&#34;&gt;11 Points WebPlotViz plot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11_poitns_example.png&#34; alt=&#34;11 Points Plot&#34;&gt;{#fig:webpviz-11}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Users can apply colors to clusters manually or choose one of the color schemes
that are provided. All the controls for the clusters are made available once
your clock on the &amp;ldquo;Cluster List&amp;rdquo; button that is located on the bottom left
corner of the plot (Third button from the left). This will pop up a window that
will allow you to control all the settings of the clusters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;features&#34;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WebPlotViz has many features that allows the users to control and customize
the plots, Other than simple 2D/3D plots, WebPlotViz also supports time series
plots and Tree structures. The examples section will show case examples for each
of these. The data formats required for these plots are not covered here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../images/webplotviz_label.png&#34; alt=&#34;WebPlotViz Features labeled&#34;&gt;{#fig:webpviz-labled}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the features are labeled in @fig:webpviz-labled. Please note that @fig:webpviz-labled
shows an time series plot so the controls for playback shown in the figure are not
available in single plots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the features are descibed in the short video that is linked in the home
page of the hosted WebPlotViz site &lt;a href=&#34;https://spidal-gw.dsc.soic.indiana.edu/&#34;&gt;WebPlotViz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;examples&#34;&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we will take a look at a couple of examples that were visualized using
WebPlotViz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;fungi-gene-sequence-clustering-example&#34;&gt;Fungi gene sequence clustering example&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following example is a plot from clustering done on a set on fungi gene
sequence data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://spidal-gw.dsc.soic.indiana.edu/public/resultsets/703979151&#34;&gt;Fungi Gene Sequence Plot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../images/webplotviz_fungi.png&#34; alt=&#34;Fungi Gene Sequence&#34;&gt;{#fig:webpviz-fungi}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;stock-market-time-series-data&#34;&gt;Stock market time series data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This example shows a time series plot, the plot were created from stock market
data so certain patterns can be followed with companies with passing years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://spidal-gw.dsc.soic.indiana.edu/public/timeseriesview/685408334&#34;&gt;Stock market data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;../../images/webplotviz_stock.png&#34; alt=&#34;Stock market data&#34;&gt;{#fig:webpviz-stock}&lt;/p&gt;

      </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
