<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Cybertraining – recognition</title><link>/tags/recognition/</link><description>Recent content in recognition on Cybertraining</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/recognition/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Report: Handwriting Recognition Using AI</title><link>/report/su21-reu-366/project/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/report/su21-reu-366/project/</guid><description>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://github.com/cybertraining-dsc/su21-reu-366/actions">&lt;img src="https://github.com/cybertraining-dsc/su21-reu-366/workflows/Check%20Report/badge.svg" alt="Check Report">&lt;/a>
&lt;a href="https://github.com/cybertraining-dsc/su21-reu-366/actions">&lt;img src="https://github.com/cybertraining-dsc/su21-reu-366/workflows/Status/badge.svg" alt="Status">&lt;/a>
Status: draft, Type: Report&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Mikahla Reeves, &lt;a href="https://github.com/cybertraining-dsc/su21-reu-366">su21-reu-366&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://github.com/cybertraining-dsc/su21-reu-366/blob/main/project/index.md">Edit&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="pageinfo pageinfo-primary">
&lt;h2 id="to-do">To-Do&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;input checked="" disabled="" type="checkbox"> Add in introduction&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;input disabled="" type="checkbox"> Add in references&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;input disabled="" type="checkbox"> Add in more images&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;input disabled="" type="checkbox"> Explain what persons have done so far, approach to the prob&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The first thing that comes to numerous minds when they hear &lt;em>Handwriting Recognition&lt;/em> is simply computers identifying handwriting,
and that is correct. Handwriting Recognition is the ability of a computer to interpret handwritten input received from different sources.
In the artificial intelligence world, handwriting recognition has become a very established area. Over the years, there have been many
developments and applications made in this field. This study investigates some of the approaches taken by researchers/developers in the
last few years to convert handwritten information from images to digital forms. Also, it discusses the importance of handwriting recognition in modern society.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Contents&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="toc">
&lt;nav id="TableOfContents">
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#1-introduction">1. Introduction&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#2-importance-of-handwriting-recognition">2. Importance of Handwriting Recognition&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#3-images">3. Images&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#4-what-has-been-done-so-far-in-the-field">4. What has been done so far in the field?&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#5-machine-learning-tools">5. Machine Learning Tools&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#6-results">6. Results&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#7-conclusion">7. Conclusion&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#8-acknowledgments">8. Acknowledgments&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="#9-references">9. References&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/nav>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Keywords:&lt;/strong> handwriting recognition, optical character recognition, deep learning.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="1-introduction">1. Introduction&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Perhaps one of the most monumental things in this modern-day is how our devices can behave like brains. Our various devices can call mom, play our favorite song,
and answer our questions by just a simple utterance of Siri or Alexa. These things are all possible because of what we call artificial intelligence. Artificial
intelligence is a part of computer science that involves learning, problem-solving, and replication of human intelligence. When we hear of artificial intelligence,
we often hear of machine learning as well. The reason for this is because machine learning also involves the use of human intelligence. Machine learning is the
process of a program or system getting more capable over time &lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. One example of machine learning at work is Netflix. Netflix is a streaming service that allows
users to watch a variety of tv shows and movies, and it also falls under the category of a recommendation engine. Recommendation engines/applications like Netflix
do not need to be explicitly programmed. However, their algorithms mine the data, identify patterns, and then the applications can make recommendations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Now, what is handwriting recognition? Handwriting Recognition is a branch of (OCR) Optical Character Recognition. It is a technology that receives handwritten
information from paper, images, and other items and interprets them into digital text in real-time &lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. Handwriting recognition is a well-established area in the
field of image processing. Over the last few years, developers have created handwriting recognition technology to convert written postal codes, addresses, math questions,
essays, and many more types of written information into digital forms, thus making life easier for businesses and individuals. However, the development of handwriting
recognition technology has been quite challenging.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One of the main challenges of handwriting recognition is accuracy. There is a wide variety of handwriting styles, both good and bad, thus making it harder for developers to
provide enough samples of what a specific character/integer looks like &lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. In handwriting recognition, the computer has to translate the handwriting into a format that it
understands, and this is where Optical Character Recognition becomes useful. In OCR, the computer focuses on a character, compares it to characters in its database, then
identifies what the letters are and fundamentally what the words are.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="2-importance-of-handwriting-recognition">2. Importance of Handwriting Recognition&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Handwriting recognition plays a vital role in the field of image processing. Any machine or technology with the capability to identify and convert handwritten
information into digital text is very valuable in almost every field work.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;input disabled="" type="checkbox"> Expound&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="3-images">3. Images&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://github.com/cybertraining-dsc/su21-reu-366/raw/main/project/images/ocr_work.jpg" alt="Figure 1">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Figure 1:&lt;/strong> Overview of Optical Character Recognition at work.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;input disabled="" type="checkbox"> MORE IMAGES&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="4-what-has-been-done-so-far-in-the-field">4. What has been done so far in the field?&lt;/h2>
&lt;h2 id="5-machine-learning-tools">5. Machine Learning Tools&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;input disabled="" type="checkbox"> Add images of the models , and the input &amp;amp; output etc&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="6-results">6. Results&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;input disabled="" type="checkbox"> Results from the papers.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="7-conclusion">7. Conclusion&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>A convincing but not fake conclusion should summarize what the conclusion of the project is.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="8-acknowledgments">8. Acknowledgments&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This paper would not have been possible without the exceptional support of Gregor von Laszewski, Carlos Theran, Yohn Jairo.
Their constant guidance, enthusiasm, knowledge and encouragement have been a huge motivation to keep going and to complete this work.
Thank you to Jacques Fleicher, for always making himself available to answer questions. Finally, thank you to Byron Greene
and the Florida A&amp;amp;M University for providing this great opportunity for undergraduate students to do research.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="9-references">9. References&lt;/h2>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Brown, S., 2021. Machine learning, explained | MIT Sloan. [online] MIT Sloan. Available at: &lt;a href="https://mitsloan.mit.edu/ideas-made-to-matter/machine-learning-explained">https://mitsloan.mit.edu/ideas-made-to-matter/machine-learning-explained&lt;/a>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Handwriting Recognition in 2021: In-depth Guide. (n.d.). &lt;a href="https://research.aimultiple.com/handwriting-recognition">https://research.aimultiple.com/handwriting-recognition&lt;/a>&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>ThinkAutomation. 2021. Why is handwriting recognition so difficult for AI? - ThinkAutomation. [online] Available at: &lt;a href="https://www.thinkautomation.com/bots-and-ai/why-is-handwriting-recognition-so-difficult-for-ai/">https://www.thinkautomation.com/bots-and-ai/why-is-handwriting-recognition-so-difficult-for-ai/&lt;/a>.&amp;#160;&lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></description></item></channel></rss>